Guide to the Common Sense Foundation Records, 1983-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Research Files Series, 1993-2008, (16 boxes and 282 electronic files) (Box 15)
  - Criminal Justice Subseries, 1997-2008 (Box 15)
    Electronic and paper files are primarily related to the foundation's work in opposition to the death penalty in North Carolina. Contains work related to Death Penalty Project 2000, a 2006 Capital Defense survey of lawyers, and a 2007 study of the death penalty and mental illness. Prominent defendants are: Zane Hill, Ricky Lee Sanderson, Charles Munsey, Wendell Flowers, Bobby Lee Harris, Henry Lee McCollum, Willy Fisher, Ernest McCarver, and Henry Lee Hunt. Other topics covered are race and the criminal justice system, juvenile justice, and mandatory minimum sentencing. Documents include correspondence, clippings, reports, research, organizing work, expenses, and contacts. Three folders contain handwritten correspondence from incarcerated people. Folders are in loose chronological order.
    - Paper files, 1997-2008 (Box 16-19)
    - Electronic files, 2000-2001 (Box 16-19)
      - Research\Death Penalty Project 2000, (53 files, 10.8 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 16-19)
  - Economic Issues Subseries, 1994-2007 (Box 16-19)
    Electronic and paper files relate to various foundation policy initiatives, including tax policy in North Carolina, corporate welfare, predatory lending, the Bill Lee Act, banking, Earned Income Tax Credit, wages, workers' rights, unionization, and workers' compensation. Also included are documents related to the North Carolina State Budget and a set of research files on specific corporations operating in the state. Documents are primarily clippings but also include email correspondence, reports, research, organizing work, and contacts. Folders are in loose chronological order.
    - Paper files, 1994-2007 (Box 19-23)
    - Electronic files, 2000 (Box 19-23)
      - Research\labor, (46 files, 22.3 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 19-23)
  - Education Subseries, 1996-2007 (Box 19-23)
    The majority of electronic and paper files relate to the foundation's participation initiatives to promote fair-testing, including grassroots organizing work in various school systems. Also included is research on charter schools, Smart Start, teacher pay, and sex education. Documents are primarily related to organizing efforts with parent groups but also include clippings, reports, and email correspondence. Folders are in loose chronological order.
    - Paper files, 1996-2007 (Box 24-26)
    - Electronic files, 1997-2000 (Box 24-26)
      - Research\ABCS, (5 folders, 153 files, 17.7 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 24-26)
      - Research\testing commission, (7 files, 346 KB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 24-26)
      - Research\ABCS, (7 files, 206 KB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 24-26)
  - North Carolina Politics Subseries, 1993-2008 (Box 24-26)
    Electronic and paper files are related to the foundation's research on campaign finance reform, elections reform, term limits, lobbyists, voter turn-out, and specific legislative and judicial races in North Carolina. Also included is research on specific politicians, including their financial holdings, and lists related to specific legislators, districts, and elections. Documents are primarily clippings but also include organizing work, email correspondence, contact lists, and reports. Folders are in loose chronological order.
    - Paper files, 1993-2008 (Box 26-27)
    - Electronic files, 2002-2004 (Box 26-27)
      - General Assembly, (8 files, 0.97 MB) (Efolder General Assembly, Box 26-27)
  - Other Research Subseries, 1995-2008 (Box 26-27)
    Contains electronic and paper files related to various other foundation policy initiatives. Documents are primarily clippings but also include organizing work, email correspondence, contact lists, and reports. Folders are grouped by topic and then arranged in loose chronological order.
    - Affirmative action, 1996 (Box 28)
    - Agriculture, 1999-2000, (2 folders) (Box 28)
      - Research\agriculture, 1999-2000, (8 files, 0.97 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 28)
    - Children, 1999-2003, (6 folders) (Box 28)
    - Drugs, 1997-1999, (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Elderly, 1997-1999, (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Environment, 1999-2007, (10 folders) (Box 28)
    - Food stamps, 2000 (Box 28)
    - Gun control, 1999-2004, (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - Health, 1997-2007, (11 of 28 folders) (Box 28)
    - Health, 1997-2007, (17 of 28 folders) (Box 29)
    - Higher education, 1999-2003, (10 folders) (Box 29)
    - Housing, 2001-2003 (Box 29)
    - Independent media, 2004 (Box 29)
    - Latinos and immigration, 1999-2008, (4 of 9 folders) (Box 29)
    - Latinos and immigration, 1999-2008, (5 of 9 folders) (Box 30)
    - LGBTQ, 2002-2007, (18 folders) (Box 30)
    - Public employees, 1999-2003, (4 folders) (Box 30)
    - Separation of church and state, 2002-2004, (4 folders) (Box 30)
    - Sexual and domestic violence, 2002-2006, (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - Tobacco, 1999-2003, (6 of 8 folders) (Box 30)
    - Tobacco, 1999-2003, (2 of 8 folders) (Box 31)
    - Tort reform, 1999-2006, (11 folders) (Box 31)
    - TV news, 1995-1998, (3 folders) (Box 31)
    - Women-owned businesses, 2002 (Box 31)
    - Unused ideas, 2002-2006, (4 folders) (Box 31)
- Staff Files Series, 1997-2008 and undated, (6454 electronic files) (Box 31)
  Contains electronic files of administrative and research documents maintained by specific staff members. Content overlaps with several different series. Arranged by staff member in original order as received. Contents have received preliminary screening for potentially confidential information; however, files will be screened before access is granted.
  - Alison, 2007-2008, (30 folders, 211 files, 23.6 MB) (Efolder Alison, Box 31)
    Contains electronic files of Alison Kiser, Associate Director. Primarily contains administrative files, including event planning, membership lists, donor letters and databases, grant applications, fundraising documents, mailings, volunteer lists and tasks, and statistics on CSF policy areas. Areas of research are EITC and affordable housing.
    Records in the subfolder "Board" are closed until June 8, 2020.
  - Brian, 2005-2007, (107 folders, 777 files, 218 MB) (Efolder Brian, Box 31)
    Contains electronic files of Brian Elderbroom, Associate Director. Administrative files include event planning, membership lists, donor letters and databases, grant applications, fundraising documents, mailings, volunteer lists and tasks, contact lists, and budgets. Principal areas of research are AIDs, bilingual education, the death penalty, environmental justice and LGBTQ issues.
    Records in the subfolder "Board of Directors" are closed until June 8, 2020.
  - Cat, 2008, (1 folder, 6 files, 328 KB) (Efolder Cat, Box 31)
    Contains electronic files of Cat Warren, Communications Director. Contains a monthly activity log and op-ed articles on collective bargaining and public transportation.
  - David, 2002-2008, (463 folders, 2,412 files, 213 MB) (Efolder David, Box 31)
    Contains electronic files of David Mills, Research Director (2002-2003) and then Executive Director (2003-2008). Documents include Mills' drafts and publications for Consider This, Common Sense Says, press releases, op-eds, and public appearances. Administrative files include hiring staff and interns, event planning, membership lists, donor letters and databases, grant applications, fundraising documents, mailings, volunteer lists and tasks, media contacts, budgets, and tax issues. Principal areas of research are charter schools, corporate welfare, the death penalty, health care, housing, immigration, LGBTQ issues, the lottery, tax policy, tobacco, tort reform, UNC tuition, lobbyists, NC elections, and the minimum wage. Also included is Mills' correspondence with incarcerated people.
  - Barbara, 2001-2002, (2 folders, 64 files, 2.85 MB) (Efolder Former Employees, Box 31)
    Contains electronic files of Barbara Shumannfang, Coordinator, Commission for Fair Testing. Documents are principally correspondence, contact lists, meeting minutes, drafts, and research related to education and fair testing.
  - ChrisF, 1997-2003, (44 folders, 1,009 files, 535 MB) (Efolder Former Employees, Box 31)
    Contains electronic files of Christ Fitzsimon, Founder and Executive Director. Documents include Fitzsimon's drafts and publications for Common Sense Legislative Update, reports, columns, and press releases. Administrative files include hiring staff, event planning, membership lists, donor letters, grant applications, fundraising documents, mailings, contact lists, budgets, and tax issues. Principal areas of research are campaign finance reform, the death penalty, mental health care reform, lobbyists, and tax inequality.
    Records in the subfolder "CSF\Board" are closed until June 8, 2020.
  - Daniella, 2001-2002, (78 folders, 726 files, 142 MB) (Efolder Former Employees, Box 31)
    Contains electronic files of Daniella Cook. Documents include Cook's drafts and publications for Burning at the Stake and fair testing updates. Administrative files include agendas and minutes of staff retreat and meetings, staff feedback, and event planning. Documents are principally related to research and organizing around issues of education and fair testing.
  - JanetC, 1998-2001, (136 folders, 783 files, 320 MB) (Efolder Former Employees, Box 31)
    Contains electronic files of Janet Cowell, Development Director. Administrative files include hiring staff, event planning, membership lists, donor letters and databases, grant applications, fundraising documents, mailings, contact lists, strategic planning, budgets, and tax issues. Principal areas of research are mental health and health care reform.
  - MeredithN, 2000-2001, (55 files, 10.8 MB) (Efolder Former Employees, Box 31)
    Contains electronic files of Meredith Nicholson, Project Director, North Carolina Death Penalty Research Study. Documents are principally correspondence, research, and organizing work related to the Death Penalty 2000 project.
  - Interns, 2003-2006, (60 folders, 295 files, 44.8 MB) (Efolder Interns, Box 31)
    Contents are organized by individual intern. Among other topics, contains research and reports related to health care, tort reform, LGBTQ issues, affordable housing, the death penalty, landfills, AIDS, workers, elections, lobbyists, and bilingual education.
  - Front Office PC\alex\Greg Work, undated, (6 folders, 86 files, 45.8 MB) (Efolder Old Machines, Box 31)
    Documents include drafts and publications for Consider This. Administrative files include contact lists, Principal areas of research are the Bill Lee Act, housing, banking, the death penalty.
  - Scott, 2008, (9 folders, 30 files, 4.33 MB) (Efolder Scott, Box 31)
    Contains electronic files of Scott Browning, Development Director. Administrative files include event planning, donor letters, grant applications, and mailings.
- Website Series, 2000s, (6040 electronic files) (Box 31)
  Contains a webcapture and backup of the foundation's website.
  [Records have been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Website files, (64 folders, 1,831 files, 77.9 MB) (Efolder common-sense.dreamhosters.com, Box 31)
  - Ketul, (83 folders, 1,736 files, 39.5 MB) (Efolder Ketul, Box 31)
  - Website, (59 folders, 1,725 files, 59.7 MB) (Efolder Website, Box 31)
  - Website-NS-Backup, (30 folders, 748 files, 25.7 MB) (Efolder Website-NS-Backup, Box 31)
- Other Materials, 2000, (1 item) (Box 31)
  - Thomas Paine Award to Congressman Mel Watt, 2000 (plaque) (Box 32)